Visual AIDS Artist Files
Visual AIDS Archive
Visual AIDS Artist Files
1994-2024
2024
Visual AIDS Archive
39 Linear Feet
Biographical / Historical
In 1994, the artist Frank Moore and arts writer David Hirsh formed the Archive Project to protect the legacies of artists who were being lost to the AIDS crisis. Moore and Hirsh were joined by Roberto Juarez, Sur Rodney (Sur), Eric Rhein, Geoff Hendricks, Ken Chu, and David Cabrera in this endeavor, and the group soon merged with Visual AIDS.
The founding principle of the Archive Project was to support any and all self-identified HIV positive artists, without adjudication. To make this possible, the project focused on creating and collecting photographic documentation of artist's work, rather than attempting to store and conserve the art objects themselves. Artists were solicited to join the archive through flyers, posters, and personal outreach. Volunteer photographers would visit artists in their homes or studios to document and catalog their artwork, providing the artist with a copy of the slides and depositing a copy into the Artist File collection. Artists (and the friends and families of deceased artists) also contributed press clippings, resumes, exhibition cards and other biographical materials to their artist files. The Artist File collection has continued to grow since its establishment in 1994, with an emphasis on digital photographs rather than slides since the late 2000s.
In the early 2000s, Visual AIDS produced several calendars featuring artwork by artists living with HIV, the Positively Art Calendar. Materials related to this competition are included in several artist files and consist of a combination of submission forms, images of artwork, and artist statement.
In addition to material donated by artists and estates, Artist Files include material related to Postcards from the Edge, a yearly Visual AIDS fundraiser. For this fundraiser, Visual AIDS solicits artwork from artists and any submission forms and unsold artworks are then added to Artist Files.
In 2014, Visual AIDS launched an online Artist Registry (visualaids.org/artists), which includes digitized images from the Artist File collection as well as images uploaded directly by artists and estates.
Scope and Contents
The Artist Files collection includes personal papers and records pertaining to the lives and work of artists living with HIV and AIDS, as well as those who have passed. The collection primarily consists of photographic documentation of artwork (both physical and digital), exhibition materials, publications, ephemera, correspondence, and personal papers and photographs. The collection contains a small number of artworks on paper, primarily unsold contributions to Visual AIDS' Postcards from the Edge fundraiser.
Arrangement
This collection is organized by artist name.
General
The Visual AIDS Artist Files collection documents HIV-positive artists. Recognizing the sensitivity of HIV disclosure, we work to confirm permission from artists and estates before publishing their name in this digital finding aid.
If you are an artist or the executor of an estate represented in this finding aid and would like to be removed, please email archive@visualaids.org.
Custodial History
Materials in the Artist Files collection have been donated by artist members, estates, friends, and family members. Additional materials have been added by Visual AIDS staff.
Artists and executors are asked to sign a release from upon initial donation of materials. The donation dates listed in this finding aid are inferred from the date on the signed release form included in artist's folder.
HIV/AIDS; Activism; AIDS activism; New York City exhibition history; Queer art; Erotic art; Gay erotic art; Community activism; Art activism; People living with HIV; HIV, AIDS, and the arts; 1990s exhibition history; 2000s exhibition history; Artwork photography; Brochures; Exhibition announcement; Personal papers; Correspondence
- David B. Abbott (b. 1953)
  Biographical / Historical
  David was born in 1953 and raised in the Boston area. He was educated at the Massachusetts College of Art. David B. Abbott's work addressed contemporary political and social issues earning him the nickname of "social realist". Abbott's 30-year career includes exhibitions in Boston, New York, Key West, Miami, Fire Island, Long Beach and San Francisco.
  Scope and Contents
  David Abbott first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998. They contain a CV, exhibition announcements, calendar submission materials, ephemera, and 35mm slides of his artwork. These materials are dated 1979-2015.
  Related Materials
  https://visualaids.org/artists/david-abbott
  - Box 1, Folder 1 (Box 1)
- Norman Bradley Abercrombie (b. 1962)
  Norman Bradley Abercrombie was born in 1962 in Tampa, Florida. He attended Georgia State University for graphic design. He lived and worked in Atlanta, Georgia.
  Norman Bradley Abercrombie first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2004. They contain examples of design work, drawings, and a self-portrait. These materials are dated 2004.
  - Box 1, Folder 2 (Box 1)
- Eric Abrams (b. 1960)
  Eric Abrams was born in 1960 in Oakland, California. His work includes acrylic on canvas, photo collage, and found object sculpture work. It has been exhibited in New York.
  Eric Abrams first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2000. They contain images of artwork with descriptions, and 35mm slide documentation of art with accompanying image list. These materials are dated 1999-2000.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/eric-abrams
  - Box 1, Folder 3 (Box 1)
- Szymon Adamczak (b. 1991)
  Szymon Adamczak was born in 1991. He is a dramaturg, writer, and performance artist. He lives in Amsterdam, the Netherlands, works for STUDIO theatregallery in Warsaw, Poland as dramaturg, and volunteers for HIV Vereniging, an organization for people living with HIV.
  Materials pertaining to Szymon Adamczak include a zine dated 2018.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/szymon-adamczak
  - Box C, Folder 7 (Box C)
- George Alan
  George Alan is a Brazilian artist who worked in New York. He studied theater design at Parsons School of Design. He works primarily in oil, pastel, and acrylic on canvas.
  George Alan first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1997. They contain correspondence, calendar submission materials, and 35mm slide documentation of artwork. These materials are dated 1997-1998.
  - Box 1, Folder 4 (Box 1)
- Alex Aleixo (1952–2008)
  Alex Aleixo was born in Brazil in 1952. He lived and worked in Los Angeles for 12 years. He held a bachelors degree in architecture from a university in Rio de Janeiro, but worked in the garment industry doing computer graphics for textiles and silkscreen.
  Alex Aleixo first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2001. They contain a CV, exhibition announcements, an artist statement, exhibition programs, and 35mm slide documentation of his work. These materials are dated 2001-2007.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/alex-aleixo
  - Box 1, Folder 5 (Box 1)
- Carlos Alfonzo (1950–1991)
  Carlos Alfonzo was born in Cuba in 1950. He received a degree in art from the Academia San Alejandro in 1973 and in art history from the University of Havana. He taught and exhibited in Cuba. He came to Miami during the Mariel boat lift in 1980 and lived and worked there. His work is in the permanent collection of the Miami-Dade Public Library.
  Materials pertaining to Carlos Alfonzo were first donated to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998 by Sena Artigas. They contain a CV and 35mm slide documentation of art with accompanying image list. These materials are dated 1976-1991.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/carlos-alfonzo
  - Box 1, Folder 6 (Box 1)
- Ali (b. 1954)
  Ali was born in 1954 in Cuba and moved to Miami, becaming an established photo artist during his time in South Beach. He received a bachelor of fine arts from the Academy of Arts College of San Francisco and attended the School of Visual Arts in New York and Chicago.
  Ali first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2005. They contain photographic prints, correspondence, exhibition materials, ephemera, and 35mm slide documentation of art. These materials are dated 1990-2011.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/ali
  - Box 1, Folder 7 (Box 1)
- Mark Allen (1961–1993)
  Mark Allen was born in 1961 in Colorado and grew up in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. He attended Southern Nazarene University and was an artist and visual merchandise designer. He died in 1993 in New York.
  Materials pertaining to Mark Allen include his artist statement, memorial materials, personal photographs, and 35mm slide documentation of art. These materials are dated 1987-1990.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/mark-allen
  - Box 1, Folder 8 (Box 1)
- Edith Alvarez (b. 1964)
  Edith Alvarez was born in 1964 in Belgium and lived and worked in New York. She received a degree in fashion design. Her artwork is primarily in painting and craft work.
  Edith Alvarez first donated material to the Visual AIDS archive in 2004. They contain an artist's biography and an image list. These materials are dated 2004.
  - Box 1, Folder 9 (Box 1)
- Marcelo Alves (b. 1970)
  Marcelo Alves was born in 1970 in Washington, DC. He studied at Parsons School of Design, Montgomery College, and the School of Visual Arts. His work is primarily in painting and drawing and has been exhibited in New York.
  Marcelo Alves first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2004. They consist of 35mm slide documentation of art. They are dated 1990-2004.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/marcelo-alves
  - Box 1, Folder 11 (Box 1)
- Rob Anderson (1953–2014)
  Rob Anderson was born in 1953. His work includes painting, drawing, and print, primarily in a realist style. In 1982, he created the iconic poster for the Gay Olympic Games (now called the Gay Games), which adapted classical Greek vase painting forms into a contemporary athletic symbol. He passed away in 2014.
  Rob Anderson first donated materials to Visual AIDS archive in 2005. They include an exhibition catalog, press clippings, a CV, a CD with images of artwork, and image lists. These materials are dated from 2003-2005.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/rob-anderson
  - Box 1, Folder 13 (Box 1)
- Stephen Andrews (b. 1956)
  Stephen Andrews was born in 1956 in Sarnia, Ontario, Canada. His work deals with memory, identity, technology and their representations in various media including drawing, animation and painting. He has exhibited his work in Canada and internationally. He is represented in the collections of the National Gallery of Canada, the Art Gallery of Ontario, the Belkin Art Gallery, the Schwartz Collection, Harvard as well as many private collections.
  Stephen Andrews first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998. They include images of artwork, CDs with images of artwork, exhibition materials, and press clippings. These materials are dated 1991-2009.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/stephen-andrews
  - Box 1, Folder 14 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 15 (Box 1)
  - Box 2, Folder 1 (Box 2)
- Patrick Angus (1953–1992)
  Patrick Angus was born in 1953 in North Hollywood, California and studied at Santa Barbara Community College, the Santa Barbara Art Institute, and the University of California, Santa Barbara. He moved to New York and worked as a security guard at the Museum of Modern Art where he was inspired to paint more. He created a large number of acrylic paintings of the inside of the Gaiety Theater, a gay male burlesque theater in Times Square, New York, and some of its dancers and customers in the 1980s. He passed away in 1992 in New York City.
  Materials pertaining to Patrick Angus include periodicals, exhibition catalogs, and an image list. These materials are dated from 1979-2019.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/patrick-angus
  - Box 2, Folder 2 (Box 2)
- Tonci Antunovic (b. 1975)
  Tonci Antunovic was born in 1975. He studied political science at the University of Zagreb in Croatia. His artwork was primarily in photography, installation, and digital art. His work has been exhibited in Croatia.
  Tonci Antunovic first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2014. They contain printouts of artist's website. These items are dated from 2014.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/tonci-antunovic
  - Box 2, Folder 4 (Box 2)
- Juan Arellano (b. 1960)
  Juan Arellano was born in 1964 in Bogota, Colombia. He studied at Columbia University, New York University, and the New School, and holds a degree in architecture. His work is primarily acrylic and oil on canvas, as well as etching.
  Juan Arellano first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998. They contain exhibition announcements, Postcards from the Edge submission materials, and 35mm slide documentation of his work. These materials are dated from 1993-1998.
  - Box 2, Folder 5 (Box 2)
- Steven Arnold (1943–1994)
  Steven Arnold was born in 1943. He received a BFA and MFA from San Francisco Art Institute. He was influential in shaping the countercultural psychedelic scene of San Francisco in the 1960s. He became Salvador Dali's protege and worked as a visionary filmmaker, photographer, painter, illustrator, set and costume designer, and assemblage artist. He passed away in 1994.
  Materials pertaining to Steven Arnold include exhibition announcements and notes on the artist. These materials are dated 2015.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/steven-arnold
  - Box 2, Folder 7 (Box 2)
- Jordan Arseneault (b. 1980)
  Jordan Arseneault was born in 1980. He is an active member of Montreal's queer performance scene. He is a drag performer, writer, meeting facilitator, and translator. His work addresses issues of queerness, gender, and social injustice.
  Materials pertaining to Jordan Arsenault include one advertisement card.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/jordan-arseneault
  - Box 2, Folder 8 (Box 2)
- Isaac Auguste (b. 1975)
  Isaac Auguste was born in 1975 in Haiti. He was educated at Ecole nationale des arts and the Institut Michel Hair Design in Port-aux-Prince. He moved to the Bronx, New York and has worked as an artistic director as well as a freelance artist and make up artist.
  Isaac Auguste first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2012. They contain Postcards from the Edge submission materials, a CV, and a CD of artwork documentation. These materials are dated from 2012.
  - Box 2, Folder 9 (Box 2)
- Dominick Avellino (b. 1944)
  Dominick Avellino was born in 1944 in New York City. His work is primarily in oil painting. It has been exhibited in New York.
  Dominick Avellino first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1997. His papers include correspondence, Postcard from the Edge submission materials, calendar submission materials, and photographs of his drawings and paintings. These materials are dated 1994-2002.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/dominick-avellino
  - Box 2, Folder 10 (Box 2)
- azt (b. 1974)
  azt was born in 1974, and lives and works in Bologna, Italy. He is a photographer primarily of male nudes. He has produced artists books and been published in contemporary art magazines and catalogs. He has exhibited in museums and private galleries across Europe and the United States.
  Materials pertaining to azt include Postcards from the Edge submission materials. These materials are dated 2017.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/azt
  - Box 2, Folder 11 (Box 2)
- Mitchell Baker (b. 1960)
  Mitchell Baker was born and raised in Manhattan. He studied at Parsons School of Design and worked in graphic design for many years. He left New York in 1995 to pursue painting. He now lives in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
  Mitchell Baker first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2001. They contain his CV and an artist's biography. These materials are dated 2001.
  - Box 2, Folder 12 (Box 2)
- Jürgen Baldiga (1959–1993)
  Jürgen Baldiga was born in 1959. He moved to Berlin in 1979 and began working in poetry, music, film, and performance art. He began to work in photography in 1985 which he used to document his life and the loss of a "culture of possibility" during the time of inhumane AIDS policies. His work has been exhibited along with excerpts from 40 of his diaries in Berlin.
  Materials pertaining to Jürgen Baldiga include an exhibition announcement. This material is dated 2023.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/juergen-baldiga
  - Box 70, Folder 8 (Box 70)
- Gregory Ball (b. 1971)
  Gregory Ball was born in 1971 in Albuquerque, New Mexico. His work includes painting, photography, sculpture, installation work, and wall design. His work has been exhibited in his own space.
  The holdings of Gregory Ball were donated to Visual AIDS by Ball in 2005. They contain photographic prints, dated 2002.
  - Box 2, Folder 14 (Box 2)
- Osvaldo Barracol (1964-1993)
  Osvaldo Barrocal was born in Panama City, Panama and came to New York via Texas. He attended the State University of New York's Empire Studio Program for independent studies in art. He passed away in 1993 at age 29 in New York.
  Materials pertaining to Osvaldo Barracol were first donated to the Visual AIDS archive by Claire McConaughy in 1998. It contains 35mm documentation of artwork. They are dated from 1988-1993.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/osvaldo-barrocal
  - Box 2, Folder 15 (Box 2)
- Amos Beaida (1960–2009)
  Amos Beaida was born in 1960 in Auburn, California and lived in Weimar, California until 1978. He started drawing when he was in his late teens and early twenties. He lived in Oregon and Texas before settling in Mountain Home, Idaho and living there until his death in March of 2009.
  Amos Beaida first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2004. It contains correspondence and 35mm slide documentation of artwork. They are dated 1982-2004.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/amos-beaida
  - Box 2, Folder 16 (Box 2)
- Robert Beard (b. 1959)
  Robert Beard was born in 1959 in Atlanta, Georgia. He studied at the University of Georgia, Athens and the School of Visual Arts. His art has been shown in various exhibitions around the United States and Europe.
  Robert Beard first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998. They contain a curatorial planning notebook, correspondence, CVs, an artist statement, digital reproductions of artwork, exhibition announcements, ephemera, and 35mm slide documentation of artwork. They are dated from 1996-2001.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/robert-beard
  - Box 2, Folder 17 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 18 (Box 2)
- Charles Bell (1935–1995)
  Charles Bell was born in 1935. His work is in American photorealist and hyperrealist large-scale still lifes. His work has appeared in various books and publications and is housed in collections at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Guggenheim, and the Hiroshima City Museum of Contemporary Art. He passed away in 1995.
  Materials pertaining to Charles Bell include a catalog of artworks, book announcement, press materials, and 35mm slide documentation of art. These materials are dated 1991.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/charles-bell
  - Box 3, Folder 1 (Box 3)
- Thomas Belloff (b. 1962)
  Thomas Belloff was born in 1962 in New Brunswick, New Jersey. He received fine arts training from the Newark School of Fine and Industrial Art as well as private instruction. His work includes paintings, linocuts, and sculpture.
  Thomas Belloff first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1998. They contain Postcards from the Edge submission materials, handwritten correspondence, ephemera, a CD, a piece of original art, and 35mm documentation of art. These materials are dated from 1989-2011.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/thomas-belloff
  - Box 3, Folder 2 (Box 3)
- Barton Lidicé Beneš (1942–2012)
  Barton Lidicé Beneš was born in 1942 in Brentwood, New Jersey. He was educated at Pratt Institute and Top Art School D'avignon in France. His work was exhibited in numerous solo and group exhibitions across the United States and Europe. He passed away in 2012 in New York City.
  Barton Lidicé Beneš first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1997. They contain exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, photographic prints of artwork, a CV, periodicals, correspondence, zines, calendar submission materials, and 35mm slide documentation of his artworks. These materials are dated from 1992-2003.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/barton-lidice-bene
  - Box 3, Folder 3 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 4 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 5 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 6 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 7 (Box 3)
- Copy Berg (Vernon E. Berg III) (1951–1999)
  Vernon E. Berg III, known as "Copy" for his close resemblance to his father, was born in Port Jefferson, New York, and attended the U.S. Naval Academy. He was the first Naval Academy alumnus to actively fight the policies against homosexuality in the services. After departing the Navy, he moved to New York and earned a master's degree in design from Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. His work includes painting, illustration, photography, and mixed media. He passed away in 1999 in New York.
  Copy (Vernon E. Berg III) Berg first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1997. They contain various exhibition announcements, postcards, Postcards from the Edge submission materials, correspondence, CVs, image lists, periodicals, 35mm slide documentation of artwork, and print-outs of artwork. These materials are dated 1990-1997.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/copy-berg
  - Box 4, Folder 2 (Box 4)
- Kermit Berg (b. 1951)
  Kermit Berg was born in 1951 in Indiana. He earned a bachelor's of art from the University of Indianapolis and studied graphic design in the graduate program there as well. He also studied digital arts at the School of the Art Institute in Chicago. His work is primarily in photography and has been exhibited numerous times in the US. He moved to Berlin in 1993.
  Kermit Berg first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 2004. They contain exhibition announcements, CDs with images of art, a wedding invitation, press clippings, image lists, photographic prints, and 35mm slide documentation of art. These materials are dated 2001-2008.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/kermit-berg
  - Box 4, Folder 4 (Box 4)
- Michael Berube (1957–2024)
  Michael Berube was born in 1957 in Endicott, NY. He obtained an associate's degree in commercial art and went on to study at SUNY Buffalo, majoring in painting. He moved to New York City to pursue a career as a performer and a painter. He was an adjunct professor at Hunter College and a curator. He passed away in 2024.
  Michael Berube first donated materials to the Visual AIDS archive in 1999. They contain exhibition announcements, Postcards from the Edge submission materials, a CD with images of artwork, periodicals, a CV, images lists, and 35mm slide documentation of artwork. These materials are dated 2000-2006.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/michael-berube
  - Box 4, Folder 6 (Box 4)
- Tom Bianchi (b. 1945)
  Tom Bianchi was born in 1945 in the suburbs of Chicago. He graduated from Northwestern University School of Law and worked as a corporate attorney. He moved to New York and became an art collector and later an artist. He started as a painter and sculptor before turning his attention to photography. He lives and works in New York.
  Materials pertaining to Tom Bianchi include a press clipping dated 1998.
  https://visualaids.org/artists/tom-bianchi
  - Box 5, Folder 1 (Box 5)
- Billy Bigs (b.1947)
  Billy Bigs was born in 1947 in New Jersey. He is a self-taught artist. His work is primarily in collage, sculpture, and photography. His work has been exhibited privately by him as well as publicly in New York.